생일 축하해!
Happy birthday!
레이첼, 왜 그래?
Rach, come on.
네 생일이야!
It's your birthday!
이 봐
Hey...
레이첼도 29살 때만큼
예쁘진 않아
She's not as pretty as
she was when she was 29.
그린 양께서 나오기 전에
몇 가지 규칙을 얘기한대
Ms. Greene wants to establish some
ground rules before she comes out.
'늙었다' '한물갔다'
'아직 쓸만하다' 그런 말은
Please don't use the words
"old" or "downhill"...
안 써줬음
고맙겠다고 하거든
or "They still look
pretty damn good."
쓸만 하거든
They do.
레이첼, 나와
Rachel, come on out.
모니카가 아침 준비했어
Monica made breakfast.
초콜렛칩 팬케이크야
Chocolate chip pancakes.
선물도 있어
We've got presents.
Good ones?
좋은 거야?
2주 전에 네가 준
목록보고 산 거야
They're all from the list
you gave us two weeks ago.
선물만 받고
29살로 남으면 안 될까?
Can I keep the presents
and still be 29?
레이첼, 서른 살이
뭐 어때서 그래?
Come on, Rach, turning 30
is not that big a deal.
그래? 네가 서른 됐을 때
아무렇지도 않았어?
Really? Is that how you felt
when you turned 30?
신이시여, 왜요?
Why, God, why?
난 안 늙게 해 준다고
약속하셨잖아요
We had a deal.
Let the others grow old, not me!
나 혼자
과민반응인 거야?
You guys, is it just me?
Am I overreacting?
아냐, 내 30번째 생일도
별로 유쾌하진 않았어
No, it's not just you.
My 30th birthday sure wasn't much fun.
챈들러까지!
And now Chandler!
우리 모두 늙어가잖아
We're all getting so old.
왜 이런 시련을
내리시나요?
Why are You doing this to us?
The One Where They All Turn Thirty
레이첼, 서른 번째
생일 축하해
네 인생의 황금기야
좋은 직장에다 좋은 친구들에다
You're in a great place in your life.
You have an amazing job, good friends.
룸메이트는 유명 탈렌트고
Your roommate's a soap opera star.
네가 맡은 역은
지금 혼수상태잖아
Your character is in a coma.
이 일로 울지 말자고
자신에게 다짐했는데
I promised myself
I wouldn't cry at this one.
내 인생도 나쁘진 않지만
많은 사람들이
I know my life's going pretty well,
but I see so many people...
서른 전에 많은
목표를 달성하잖아
who've accomplished their goals
before they're 30.
그렇지만 나하고
비교해선 안 되지
Yeah, but you shouldn't compare
yourself to me.
- 어서, 피비!
- 넌 할 수 있어
-Come on, Phoebe!
-You can do it!
- 어서
- 거 봐
-Come on.
-There you go.
내가 해냈어!
호피티 타고 1.5킬로 완주
I did it!
One mile on a Hippity Hop.
서른 전에 하고 싶은 일
이제 다 했다
That's everything I wanted to do
before I was 30.
언니하고 화해하는
일만 빼놓고
Except I wanted to
patch things up with my sister.
그렇지만 신난다!
Oh, well. But, yeah!
얘들아, 이거 죽인다
내 말뜻 알지?
Girls, this thing is a godsend,
if you know what I mean.
Let's have some fun.
What do you want to do?
분위기 좀 띄우자
자기 뭐하고 싶어?
아무 것도 하기 싫어
I don't want to do anything.
로스처럼 30번째 생일에
멍청한 짓하는 것보단 낫다
Doing nothing on your 30th is better
than doing something stupid, like Ross.
필요해서 산 거였어
That was a practical purchase.
출퇴근용으로
차가 필요했다구
I needed that car for transportation.
알아? 난 애도 있다고
Okay? I have a child.
나 정말 멋있지
How hot do I look in this?
로스가 스포츠카를?
Ross, a sports car?
그냥 바지 속에 양말이나
쑤셔넣는 게 싸게 먹히지 않나?
Wouldn't it be cheaper
to just stuff a sock down there?
그런 게 아니야
That's not what this is about.
난 스포츠카 광이야
I am a sports car enthusiast.
- 나 원래 차 좋아하잖아
- 몇 마력인데?
-I've always been into cars.
-What's the horsepower?
몰라, 그래도
반짝반짝하잖아
I don't know, but look how shiny!
이 차를 사다니
-I can't believe you bought this.
-So can I have a ride, stud?
나 좀 태워줄래, 자기?
타
Hop in.
네 생애 최고의
드라이브를 기대하시라
Get ready for the
smoothest ride of your life.
젠장
Damn it.
좋아, 다음은 누구야?
Okay, who's next?
아줌마처럼 그냥 앉아서
보내진 않을 거야
I am gonna do something today. I
won't sit around like some old lady.
어딜 뚫어볼까?
I want to get something pierced.
코나 혀 같은 데
Like my nose or my tongue or something.
그래? 되게 아픈데
Really? Because that hurts.
어때서?
내가 보기엔...
So what?
The way I see it..
아야, 이게!
Son of a bitch!
자기 기분 이해해
Look, I know what
you're going through.
나도 25살 된단
생각하면 겁나거든
I'm totally freaked out
about turning 25.
당장 나가
Get out of my apartment.
레이첼, 너 잘하고 있어
Rach, I think that you're doing great.
솔직히 이만하면
다른 애들보다 나아
Let's face it,
no one handles this well.
특히 모니카보다는
Least of all you.
다시 묶어
모니카 곧 올 거야
Put that back on.
Monica will be here any minute.
조이 목젖이 아프단 말야
But it hurts my Joey's apple.
다시 말하지만 조이는
빼고 말해도 돼
For the last time, it's not named
after each individual man.
챈들러, 파티 준비 잘 했어
모든 게 멋있어
You've done a wonderful job with
the party. Everything's so lovely.
어머님만큼은 아니죠
Well, not as lovely as you.
서른 살 먹은 따님이
있다니 믿어지지 않네요
I can't believe you have a
30-year-old daughter.
그 턱시도가 30년이나
됐다는 것도 믿어지지 않고요
And I can't believe you have
a tux that's 30 years old.
그보다 오래 됐지
이거 입고 로스를 만들었거든
It's older than that. Ross was
conceived right near this tuxedo.
다들 숨어요
모니카가 와요
Everybody hide!
She's coming.
전부 엎드려요!
Everybody down!
다들 여기 계세요
제가 나가 보죠
Everybody stay here.
I'll find out what's going on.
자기가 문열어주네
Hey, you got the door open!
취했어?
Hey, are you drunk?
아니
No.
응
Okay.
좋아
See, I was a little nervous
about turning...
서른 살이 된다는 게
30.
좀 서글퍼서
So the busboys took me out
for some drinks.
웨이터들하고 한 잔 했거든
Might want to puke on you later.
나중에 토할지도 몰라
Here's the thing. We've thrown
a very formal surprise party for you.
있잖아, 너한테
깜짝파티를 열었거든
-Your parents and friends are in there.
-No!
- 친구들과 부모님 와 계셔
- 설마!
-Yes! Yes!
-No.
- 맞아!
- 안 돼!
Oh, no! My parents have never
seen me drunk.
엄마 아빤 나 취한 거
한 번도 못 보셨어
That they know of.
적어도 그렇게 생각하시지
We'll get you some coffee.
They'll never know that you're drunk.
커피 좀 마셔
그럼 취한 줄 모르실 거야
-You promise?
-I'll take care of it.
- 그럴까?
- 내가 알아서 할게
I love you so much.
자기 사랑해
Okay, we have to do something
about your breath.
알았어, 입냄새부터
어떻게 해야겠다
What about your breath?
자기 입냄샌 어떻고?
That's still yours.
자기 입냄새야
Now remember,
it's a surprise party.
깜짝 파티란 걸
명심해
So when you go in, act surprised.
들어가면 놀란 척해
Ready?
준비?
Surprise!
서프라이즈!
Okay, forward. Forward.
자, 앞으로, 앞으로
Stop!
멈춰!
Okay, back.. Stop!
좋아, 뒤로...멈춰!
Okay, for.. Stop!
좋아, 앞...멈춰!
Stop! Stop!
멈춰! 멈춰!
자, 이렇게 해보자
Okay, here's what we're gonna do.
내가 이 차 문을 따고 들어가
기어를 중립에 놓으면
I'll break into this minivan,
put it in neutral.
넌 앞으로 밀고
로스가 차를 빼는 거야
You push it forward
so Ross can get out of the spot.
좋아, 시작하자
All right. Here we go.
튀어!
Haul ass!
서른 번째 생일 축하해!
Happy 30th birthday! Here.
동심의 언니와 성인인 언니
둘 다를 위한 거야
It's for the child in you.
And the woman.
서른 번째 생일 축하해!
Happy 30th!
왜 계속 그 말을 하는 거야?
Why do you keep saying that?
서른 번째 생일이니까
Because it's our 30th birthday.
아냐, 우린 서른이 아니라
서른 한 살이야
Yeah, no, we're not 30.
We're 31. Okay.
잠깐
Wait.
너였구나
Oh, it's you.
뭐라고?
Yeah. What?
우린 서른 하나라니까
Yeah, we're not 30. We're 31.
출생증명서를 보면
알 수 있어
That's what it says
on my birth certificate.
언니 출생증명서도 있어?
You have a birth certificate?
내 엄마 돌아가셨을 때
받은 상자에 들어 있었어
I got a big box of family stuff
when my mom died.
Our mom.
우리 엄마지
그렇다고 해두자
Right. Okay.
- 내 것도 있어?
- 아니, 불법체류자에게 팔았어
-Do you have mine?
-No, I sold it to a Swedish runaway.
맙소사
Oh, my God.
맙소사, 서른 한 살이네!
Oh, my God, we are 31!
그래
Yeah.
내 인생에서
1년을 잃었잖아
I just lost a whole year of my life.
그래
Okay.
- 중간이름이 파멜라야?
- 그래
-Your middle name is Pamela?
-Yes.
내건 모르는데
혹 언닌 기억해?
I never knew mine.
Do you remember what it is?
Yes.
그래, 피비잖아
Phoebe.
- 그건 그냥 내 이름이지
- 그럼 몰라
-That's my first name.
-Right. Okay. Then, no.
거실을 통과해왔으니
잘 하고 있는 거야
We made it across the room.
You're doing great.
무슨 일이야?
What's going on?
모니카가 취했거든
Monica's a little drunk.
신난다! 난 취한
모니카가 좋더라
Yeah! I love drunk Monica.
안 취했을 때보다
훨씬 재미있어
Oh, she's so much more fun
than regular Monica.
부모님이 모르시게
하고 싶어해
She doesn't want her parents to know.
좋아, 그럼 이렇게 하자
All right, all right.
Here's what we'll do.
내가 두 배로 취하면
모니카 취한 줄 모를 거야
I'll get twice as drunk,
then no one will even notice her.
무슨 일이야?
What's going on?
모니카 취했어
Monica's wasted.
그럼 파티가
더 재미있어지겠네
Maybe that'll liven up this party.
옷 갈아입히는 거
좀 도와줘
Will you just help her get changed?
술취한 여자 옷 벗기는 건
조이 전문 아냐?
Taking care of a drunk, naked woman
seems like a job for Joey.
이건 내 선물
This one's from me.
목록엔 없었지만 좋아할 거야
It wasn't on your list,
but it's really fun.
스쿠터네
A scooter.
목록에 있는 걸 사야지
Stick to the list.
항상 목록에 있는 걸로 사
Always stick to the list.
아냐, 마음에 들어
고마워
No, no, I love it. Thank you.
다음은 우리 것 열어 봐!
Open ours next! Open ours next!
둘이 사귄다고
선물도 하나야?
Now that you're a couple,
we don't get two gifts?
넌 내 생일선물로
한 번 안아주고 끝났잖아
For my last birthday,
you gave me a hug.
카드 읽어 봐!
Read the card! Read the card!
'생일 축하해, 할머니'
"Happy birthday, Grandma.
'죽어 땅속에 묻히는 것보단'
It's better to be over the hill...
'한물 간 게 더 낫지'
than buried under it.
'사랑을 담아, 모니카와
챈들러' 재밌다
All our love, Monica and Chandler."
That's funny.
그러지 마, 농담이야
No, no. That was a joke.
알아, 재밌어
I know, I get it. It's funny.
넌 할머니 아니잖아
Because you're not a grandma.
할머니가 되려면
결혼하고 애도 있어야지
To be a grandma, you have to
be married and have children.
난 미혼에 애도 없으니까
재미있다는 거야
I don't have any of those things.
That's why it's so funny.
잠깐 실례할게...
I'm just gonna go...
카드 하나도
변변히 못 고르고
All you had to do was buy the card.
남편과 애가 없다고
속상해 할 이유가 없지
It was stupid to get upset about
not having a husband and kids.
계획을 세우면 되니까
All I really needed was a plan.
난 애 셋 낳을거거든
See, I want three kids.
너도 네 동생을 위해
세 쌍동이 낳아주게?
And you want to have them all at the
same time and all for your brother.
그러니까...
As I was saying...
서른 다섯까진 첫 애를
낳고 싶으니까
I should have the first one
by the time I'm 35.
아직 5년이 남았네
Which gives me five years.
If I want a kid when I'm 35, I don't
have to get pregnant until I'm 34.
35살에 애 낳으려면
34살에 임신하면 되고
Which gives Prada four years
to start making maternity clothes.
프라다가 임산복 런칭할
시간이 4년 있지
하지만 애를 갖기 전 1년쯤은
결혼생활이 하고 싶은데
But I want to be married
for a year before I get pregnant.
Really? That long?
정말? 그렇게나 오래?
Look all you want, it's happening.
뭘 봐
그렇게 될 건데
I don't have to get married until
I'm 33. That's three whole years.
33살에 결혼하면 되니
3년이나 남았네
Wait a minute, though.
잠깐만
I'll need a year and a half
to plan the wedding.
결혼식 계획에
1년 반 걸릴 거고
And I'd like to know the guy
for a year, year and a half...
약혼 전에 1년이나
1년 반 정도
before we get engaged.
사귀고 싶은데
Which means I need to meet the guy
by the time I'm 30.
그럼 30살엔 그 남잘
만나야 되는 거잖아
Which is fine
because you just turned...
괜찮아, 왜냐하면
넌 겨우
28!
28살이니까!
No, Ross. No, it is not fine.
아냐, 로스
괜찮지 않아
I should already be with
the guy I'm gonna marry.
내가 결혼할 남자를
지금쯤 만났어야 해
Will you quit hogging it?
혼자만 타지 좀 마
I'm telling you, it's like
watching Bambi learn how to walk.
꼭 밤비 걸음마 배우는 거
보는 거 같다니까
취했대요
You're drunk.
엄마 아빠 화낼 거래요
Mom and Dad are gonna be mad.
나도 조금 취했나봐
Maybe I'm a little drunk.
게살 케이크예요?
Are those crab cakes?
그거 나오면 바로
나한테 갖고 오랬잖아요
I told you to come straight to me
when they were ready.
좀 어때?
How you feeling?
자기 진짜 핸섬하다
You are so handsome.
당장 여기서 사랑을
나누고 싶은데
I want to make love to you
right here, right now.
안 그랬음 좋겠는데
I really wish that you wouldn't.
조금만 참으면
곧 잘 수 있을 거야
Just get through a little bit more,
then we can put you in bed.
미소만 짓고
아무하고도 말 하지 마
Just smile, and don't talk to anyone.
여러분, 오늘의
주인공 얘길 들어보죠
Speech, speech!
Let's hear from the birthday girl.
피비!
Phoebe!
거봐, 다들 날 쳐다보잖아
See, everybody's looking at me.
계획대로 되어 가잖아
The plan's working.
내 윗도리 아직
벗지도 않았는데
I didn't even have to
take off my top yet.
한 마디 해라!
Speech. Come on, speech!
한시도 손을 뗄 수가
없는 게로군
You can't keep your hands off her
for one second.
보기 좋잖아요
I think it's nice.
어쩔 수 없거든요
I think it's necessary.
다들 와주셔서 고마워요
I want to thank you all for coming.
우리 가족과
My family and...
내 친구들
my friends.
제가 하고 싶은 말은...
I'd really like to say that I'm...
하고 싶은 말이
뭔지 아세요?
You know what I'd really like to say?
난 취했어요!
I'm drunk!
맞아요, 엄마, 아빠
That's right, Mom and Dad.
엄마 아빠 꼬맹이 딸이
술독에 빠졌어요
Your little old "Harmomica" is hammered.
또 있는데
And guess what?
이번이 처음이
아니에요
I've been drunk before.
담배도 피워봤고요
And I've smoked a cigarette.
It's all okay.
It's okay because...
다 괜찮아요
왜냐하면
I turned 30 today.
난 서른 살이거든요
And I can do anything I want.
내 마음대로 할 수 있다고요
Because I am a grownup.
난 어른이니까요
Okay, quick. Help me get this off.
빨리, 이것 벗는 거
좀 도와 줘
1년이 없어졌어
I lost a whole year.
너무 속상해
이럴 수는 없다구!
I can't believe it.
This is so unfair!
피비, 괜찮아
Come on, Phoebe, it'll be okay.
그래? 그럴까?
Will it? Will it?
네가 서른 한 살인 것을
알았다면 넌 어떻겠어?
How would you feel if
you found out you were 31?
그런 일은 없어
새로 거래를 했거든
That's not gonna happen.
Because we have a new deal.
스케줄도 엉망이
되어 버렸고
Plus, it ruined my schedule.
서른 한 살까지 해 보고
싶던 일을 하나도 못 했잖아
I haven't done the things
I wanted to do before I was 31.
- 어떤 거?
- 포르투갈 사람 만나는 거
-Like what?
-Like I haven't met any Portuguese people.
완벽한 키스하는 거
I haven't had the perfect kiss.
저격수 양성소에도
가고 싶었단 말야
And I haven't been to sniper school.
우리 가서
생일 케이크나 좀 먹자
Why don't we go and
have some birthday cake?
좀 혼자 있고 싶어
나중에 보자, 고마워
I just feel like being by myself.
See you guys later. Thanks.
불쌍한 피비
Poor Phoebe.
저기 있잖아, 내가
피비 바래다주고 올게
Hey, you guys, I think
I'm gonna walk her home.
- 이런
- 왜?
-Oh, man.
-What?
조이 케이크 먹으러 간 거야
He's gonna eat the cake.
피비!
Phoebe!
저기...
Listen, I...
눈 감아 봐
Close your eyes.
이제 한 가지는 했지?
That's one thing to
cross off your list.
그래
Oh, yeah.
게다가 난 16분의 1은
포르투갈 인이야
Plus, I'm one-sixteenth Portuguese.
좋아, 준비 됐지?
Okay, is everybody clear?
다 함께 들어서
We're gonna pick it up...
옮기는 거다
and move it.
팀워크가 필요해
차를 들어서
All we need is teamwork.
We're gonna lift the car...
빼내는 거야
and slide it out.
들어서
Lift...
빼
and slide.
- 로스, 내 생각엔...
- 들어서
-Ross, I really don't think this..
-Lift...
빼
and slide.
- 좋아, 시작한다
- 다들 준비됐지?
-Okay, here we go.
-All right, everyone.
들어서
Lift...
빼는 거다
and slide.
-Hey, Joey..
-Come on, Rach, my turn just started.
- 조이...
- 방금 내 차례 됐단 말야
태그한테 할 얘기 있어
Actually, I just want to talk to Tag.
알았어
이거 밖에서 타도 돼?
Oh, okay.
Hey, can I ride this outside?
맘대로 해
내가 네 엄마냐?
Whatever. I'm not your mother.
찻길에선 안 돼!
Not in the street!
- 기분 좀 나아졌어?
- 응, 괜찮아, 난 그냥...
-Are you feeling any better?
-Yeah, I'm doing okay. I'm...
얘기 좀 해
Let's talk.
왜 그래
What's up?
태그...
Oh, Tag...
태그는 정말 괜찮은 남자야
같이 있음 즐겁고
You're such a great guy.
And we have so much fun together.
- 그렇지만...
- 잠깐만
-But I..
-Wait.
무슨 얘길 하려는지
알 것 같아
I think I see where you're going.
그 전에 내가 한 마디
해도 될까?
Before you say anything else,
can I say one more thing?
좋은 지적이야
Well said.
내가 말했던 재미가
바로 그런 걸 말하는 거야
And a good example of the fun
I was referring to.
그렇지만 더 이상
재미만으론 살 수 없어
But I think I'm past the point
where I can just have fun.
레이첼, 서른 살이 됐다고
이럴 필요는 없잖아
Don't do this. This is just
because you're turning 30.
아냐, 필요해
Yeah, it is.
자기는 아직 어려
25살이잖아
But you're just a kid.
I mean, you're 25.
- 사실은 24살인데
- 맙소사
-Twenty-four, actually.
-Oh, God.
태그가 여섯 살만 더 많다면
정말 좋을 텐데
You know what I wish?
I wish you were six years older.
Well, if I'm wishing for stuff,
I wish I was six years younger.
사실은 내가 여섯 살
적었으면 더 좋겠고
-Me too.
-Yeah. Sorry.
- 나도
- 그러게, 미안해
Hey, how'd it go?
어떻게 됐어?
If I only want two kids,
can I keep him for another year?
애 둘만 낳기로 하고
태그와 1년 더 사귀면 안 될까?
You did the right thing.
잘한 거야
I don't like this anymore.
이제 이거 안 할래
Well, here we are.
Just a bunch of 30-year-olds.
우리 전부
서른 살이 되었구나
Do you realize in 10 years
we're gonna be 40?
10년 후면 전부
40살이겠네?
Why, God?
신이시여
Why are you doing this to us?
왜 이런 시련을
내리시나이까?
Yes! My baby's finally free.
드디어 공간이 생겼다
All right!
신난다!
Start it up. Let's go!
시동 걸어, 출발하자!
How hot are we?
우리 멋있죠?
You want to buy a car?
너 차 안 살래?